Thank y'all!
شكراً لكم جميعاً
This is going to be a motivational speech.
ستكون هذه المحادثة تحفيزية.
Because --
لأنه --
imagine my motivation standing between this strong, healthy crowd ...
تخيلوا حماستي حائرة بين هذا الحضور الرائع
and lunch.
ووجبة الغداء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So ...
لذلك...
I'm @Falkvinge on Twitter.
هذا حسابي على تويتر Falkvinge@
Feel free to quote me if I say something memorable, stupid, funny, whatever.
لا تترددوا في اقتباسي إذا قلت شيئاً بارزاً، أو مُضحكاً، أو أياً كان.
I love seeing my name on Twitter.
فأنا اُحب أن أرى اسمي على تويتر.
So ...
لذلك ...
Hi! I'm Rick.
مرحباً ، أنا ريك.
I'm a politician.
أنا رجل سياسي.
I'm sorry.
أنا آسف.
How many in here have heard of the Swedish Pirate Party before?
كم منكم هنا سمعوا عن حزب القرصان السويدي من قبل؟
Let's see a show of hands.
ارفعوا أيديكم.
OK, that's practically everybody.
حسناً، تقريباً الجميع.
Probably due to the fact that we are Sweden's neighbor.
ربما لأننا جيران للسويد.
I frequently ask how many have heard of any other political party
في العادة أسأل كم عدد اللذين سمعوا عن حزب آخر
and there's always just scattered hands in the audience
ودائماً تُرفع بعض الأيادي المتناثرة بين الحضور
compared to this first question which is one-half to two-thirds.
مقارنة بالسؤال الأول الذي ترفع فيه نصف الأيدي أو ثلثيها.
This is actually the first time ever that does not match.
الحقيقية هذه أول مرة لا يحدث فيها نفس الشيء.
It was practically everybody.
الجميع تقريباً رفع يده.
So, for those who haven't heard of us:
إذاً، للذين لم يسمعوا بنا:
well, the Pirate Party, we love the net.
في حزب القرصان، نحن نُحب الإنترنت.
We love copying and sharing, and we love civil liberties.
نُحب النسخ والمشاركة وكذلك الحريات المدنية.
For that, some people call us pirates.
لهذا، يسمينا البعض بالقراصنة.
Probably in an attempt to make us bow our heads and feel shame.
ربما محاولة منهم لجعلنا نُخفض رؤوسنا ولنشعر بالخزي.
That didn't work very well.
و هذا لم يُجدي كثيراً.
We decided to stand tall about it instead.
بل قررنا أن نظل شامخين حيال هذا الأمر.
And so in 2006, I founded a new political party.
في سنة 2006، قمت بتأسيس حزب سياسي جديد.
I led it for its first five years.
وتوليت قيادته في سنواته الخمس الأولى.
And the European elections, the last European elections,
وفي الانتخابات الأوروبية، الانتخابات الأوروبية الأخيرة،
we became the largest party
أصبحنا أكبر حزب
and the most coveted youth demographic, sub-30.
و الأكثر شعبية بين فئة الشباب تحت سن الثلاثين.
And what's interesting is we did that
والمثير للاهتمام أننا فعلنا هذا
on less than one percent of the competition's budget.
بأقل من 1% من الميزانية المحددة للحملة الانتخابية.
We had a campaign budget total of 50,000 euros.
كانت ميزانية حملتنا الانتخابية تبلغ 50.000 يورو.
They had six million between them -- and we beat them.
و كان مجموع ميزانية منافسينا تبلغ ستة ملايين وقد هزمناهم.
That gave us a cost efficiency advantage of over two orders of magnitude.
وهذا أعطانا ميزة تكلفة الفعالية بمقدار أسي أكبر من 2.
And I'm gonna share the secret recipe of how we did that.
وساُشارككم الوصفة السحرية عن كيفية قيامنا بذلك.
We developed swarm methodologies.
لقد قمنا بتطوير مناهج السرب.
And they can be applied to any business or social cause.
التي يمكن تطبيقها على أي عمل أو قضية اجتماعية.
Well, almost any --
حسناً، تقريباً أي منها --
there's a small asterisk by the end,
هناك نقطة صغيرة في النهاية،
and I'll get to that in just a minute.
وسأتطرق إليها بعد دقيقة واحدة فقط.
But applying these --
لكن بتطبيق هذه --
and we've done this dozens of times, we know that this works.
لقد طبقنا ذلك عشرات المرات ونعرف بأن الأمر ناجح.
We've put two people in the European Parliament,
وضعنا شخصين في البرلمان الأوروبي،
we have 45 people in various German state parliaments,
لدينا 45 شخصاً في مختلف برلمانات الولايات الألمانية،
we're in the Icelandic parliament, the Czech senate,
ونتواجد أيضاً بالبرلمان الإيسلندي ومجلس الشيوخ التشيكي،
many, many, many more, local councils --
وفي العديد العديد من المجالس المحلية --
and, as said, we've spread to 70 countries.
وحسبما يُقال، لقد انتشرنا في 70 دولة.
And that's not bad for a political movement
وهذا ليس بالأمر السيء بالنسبة لحركة سياسية
that hasn't even been around for a decade.
لم يتجاوز عمرها العقد.
So today we're going to talk a bit about --
حسنا، سنتحدث اليوم قليلًا حول --
how people are motivated to be part of change,
كيف يتم تحفيز الناس ليكونوا جزءاً من التغيير،
to be part of something bigger than themselves.
ليكونوا جزءاً من أمر أكبر من ذواتهم.
And how you can channel this into an organization
وعن كيفية احتواء ذلك الشعور في إطار منظمة
that harnesses this great power of wanting to make the world a better place.
تسخر تلك الطاقة الكبيرة لجعل العالم مكاناً أفضل للعيش.
And in the end, come out a little on the better.
وفي النهاية، الاقتراب قليلاً من الأفضل.
When I speak to businesspeople, I frequently make them very upset
عندما أتحدث مع رجال الأعمال، عادة ما أجعلهم جد مستائين
when I contradict them
عندما أعارضهم
and say that no, your employees are not your most valuable asset.
وأخبرهم لا، موظفيكم ليسوا أثمن أصولكم.
Your most valuable asset is the thousands of people
أثمن أصولكم هم الآلاف من الناس
who want to work for you for free.
الراغبين في العمل عندكم دون مقابل.
And you don't let them.
وأنتم تمنعونهم من ذلك.
They get very upset about that.
إنهم يستاؤون جدا من هذا القول.
A swarm is a congregation of tens of thousands of volunteers
السرب هو تجمع لعشرات الآلاف من المتطوعين
that have chosen of their own will to converge on a common goal.
الذين اختاروا برضاهم العمل نحو هدف مشترك.
There's this "Futurama" quote:
هناك مقولة لرسوم "فيوتشوراما" تقول:
"When push comes to shove, you gotta do what you love --
"عندما يجد الجد، يجب عليك القيام بما تحب --
even if it's not a good idea."
حتى ولو لم تكن فكرة جيدة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, seriously, what kind of idiot thinks
أقصد، بصدق، من الغبي الذي كان ليفكر
they can change the world by starting a political party?
بأنهم قادرون على تغيير العالم بتأسيس حزب سياسي؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This kind of idiot, apparently.
من الواضح أن هذا الغبي.
But it works!
لكن الأمر نجح!
What you need to do is to put a stake in the ground.
ما عليكم فعله هو بدء الخطوة الأولى على الطريق.
You need to announce your goal.
عليكم الإعلان عن هدفكم.
Just say, "I want to accomplish this."
فقط قولوا: "أريد تحقيق هذا الأمر."
I'm going to do this.
سأفعل هذا الأمر.
And it doesn't need to be very costly.
ولا يحتاج الأمر أن يكون مكلفاً.
My announcement was just two lines in a chat channel.
كان إعلاني عبارة عن سطرين في قناة دردشة.
"Hey, look, the Pirate Party has its website up now after New Year's."
"مرحبا، اسمعوا، يفتتح حزب القرصان موقعه الإلكتروني بعد السنة الجديدة"
And the address.
والعنوان الإلكتروني.
That was all the advertising I ever did.
كان ذلك الإعلان الوحيد الذي قمت به.
The next time I had several hundred activists wanting to work with us.
في المرة التالية كان لدي عدة مئات من النشطاء الراغبين في العمل معنا.
When you provide such a focus point,
عندما تقدم مسألة مركزة من هذا النوع،
a swarm intelligence emerges.
يظهر ذكاء السرب.
When people can rally to a flag.
عندما يتكاثف الناس خلف راية واحدة.
And that's what gives you this two orders of magnitude of cost efficiency.
وهذا ما يمنحكم تلك الفعالية بالتكلفة بمقدار أسي هو 2.
It's a huge advantage --
وهي ميزة ضخمة --
you're running circles around all the legacy organizations.
نحن أفضل من المنظمات التقليدية.
And there are four goals that need to be fulfilled in your goal
هناك أربعة مبادئ يجب تحقيقها ضمن هدفكم الرئيسي
in order for this to work.
بالترتيب لينجح الأمر.
These four criteria are that your goal must be:
هذه المبادئ الأربعة هي أن يكون هدفكم:
tangible, credible, inclusive and epic.
ملموساً وواقعياً وشاملاً وملحمياً.
Let's take a look at them: It needs to be tangible.
دعونا نلقي نظرة عن قرب عليها: يجب أن يكون ملموساً.
A lot of people say,
الكثير من الناس يقولون:
"Well, you know, we should make the world a better place,"
"حسنا، تعلمون، ينبغي أن نجعل العالم مكاناً أفضل للعيش."
or, "Yeah, we should all feel good now."
أو "نعم، ينبغي أن نشعر بالراحة جميعاً الآن."
Not going to work.
هذا الأمر لن ينجح.
You need a binary.
أنتم بحاجة إلى نظام ثنائي.
Are we there yet, or are we not there yet?
هل وصلنا أم لم نصل بعد؟
It needs to be credible.
يجب أن يكون واقعياً.
Somebody seeing the project plan that you're posting needs to see
الشخص الذي يطلع على مخطط مشروعكم
that, yes, this project plan will take us
يجب أن يرى أنه، نعم، هذا مخطط مشروع سيوصلنا
from where we are to where we want to be.
من مكاننا إلى المكان المنشود.
You need to break it down into subgoals
عليكم تقسيمه إلى أهداف فرعية
that each by themselves are seen as doable,
بحيث يكون كل هدف قابل للتحقيق على حدة،
and when you add the subgoals together,
وعندما تجمعون الأهداف الفرعية معاً،
we've gone to where we want.
نبلغ المكان المنشود.
It needs to be --
يجب أن يكون --
and this is where it gets exciting in terms of working swarmwise --
وهذه هي النقطة حيث تصبح الأمور مثيرة من حيث العمل بذكاء السرب --
it needs to be inclusive.
يجب أن يكون الهدف شاملاً.
Anybody who sees this project plan needs to immediately say,
حيث أن كل من يطلع على مخطط هذا المشروع يجب أن يقول:
"I want to do this -- and there's my spot!"
"أريد أن أفعل هذا -- هذا مكاني!"
And they will be able to jump right into the project
وسيكون بإمكانهم الاندماج مباشرةً في المشروع
and start working on it without asking anybody's permission.
والبدء في العمل عليه دون استئذان أحد.
And that is exactly what'll happen.
وهذا بالضبط ما سيحصل.
And, last but not least, it needs to be epic.
وأخيراً وليس آخراً، يجب أن يكون الهدف ملحمياً.
It needs to energize people. It needs to electrify people.
يجب أن يحث الناس. يجب أن يحض الناس.
Shoot for the moon!
اطلبوا القمر!
On second thought, don't shoot for the moon,
بعد إعادة النظر، لا داعي لطلب القمر،
we've already been there -- shoot for Mars!
سبق وأن وصلنا إليه -- اطلبوا المريخ!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In contrast,
في المقابل،
you will never be able to get a volunteer swarm forming
لن تتمكنوا قط من جذب متطوعين لتكوين سرب
around making the most correct tax audit ever.
خاص بتكوين أفضل فريق تدقيق ضريبي.
Doesn't electrify people. Go to Mars.
ذلك لا يحض الناس. الذهاب إلى المريخ.
A lot of people kind of balk at the obstacles.
الكثير من الناس يترددون نوعاً ما أمام العقبات.
We're going to climb a huge mountain.
سنصعد جبلاً شامخاً.
So how do you motivate people to do that?
إذاً، كيف تحفز الناس لفعل ذلك؟
Well, it turns out that obstacles are not the problem.
حسناً، لقد تبين أن العقبات ليست المشكل.
Not knowing the obstacles is the problem.
بل عدم معرفة العقبات هو المشكل.
If you know how high the mountain is,
إذا كنت تعرف ارتفاع الجبل،
you know exactly what it takes to scale it.
فستعرف بالضبط ما سيتطلبه الأمر لصعوده.
We know exactly how far away Mars is and what it takes to get there.
نحن نعرف بالضبط كم يبعد المريخ عنا وما يتطلبه الأمر للوصول إليه.
If you can plan it like a project,
إن تمكنتم من التخطيط للأمر كمشروع،
you can plan what resources you need
ستقدرون على تحديد أي الموارد ستحتاجونها
and you can execute it, exactly like a project.
وستتمكنون من تنفيذ الأمر، تماما كأي مشروع.
Let's see: we're going to Mars,
دعونا نرى: سنذهب إلى المريخ،
we need two dozen volunteer rocket scientists,
سنحتاج إلى أربع وعشرين عالم فضاء متطوع،
one dozen volunteer metallurgists,
واثني عشر عالم معادن متطوعين،
some crazy dude who will mix rocket fuel in his backyard
والمجنون الذي سيحضّر وقود الصاروخ في حديقته الخلفية
and so on.
وهلم جراً.
When you can list the resources, you know what you need to get there.
عندما تعدون قائمة الموارد، ستعرفون ما ستحتاجونه للوصول إلى هناك.
When you know what you need to get there, you can go there.
عندما تعرفون ما ستحتاجونه للوصل إلى هناك، يمكنكم إذا الانطلاق.
And the next thing is to encourage this development of a swarm intelligence,
والأمر التالي هو تشجيع تكوين ذكاء السرب،
which is where the cost efficiency comes in.
حيث تأتي تتدخل فعالية التكلفة.
There's a TED Talk on motivation that debunks that we work for money,
هناك محادثة TED حول التحفيز تضحد الاعتقاد القائل أننا نعمل لأجل المال،
and it presents science on how we're really motivated by three things,
وتوضح بشكل علمي كيف أننا نتحفز بالفعل بثلاثة أمور،
in terms of larger creative tasks,
من حيث مهام الابتكار الكبيرة،
when we work for something bigger than ourselves.
عندما نعمل لأمر أكبر من ذواتنا.
We work for autonomy, mastery and purpose.
نحن نعمل من أجل التحرر والتفوق والهدف.
We've covered purpose already.
وقد ضمنا الهدف بالفعل.
As in, working for something bigger, tangible, credible, inclusive and epic.
بالعمل لأمر عظيم وملموس ومعقول وشامل وملحمي.
So, where that motivation talk ends,
وبهذا تنتهي محادثة التحفيز،
what it doesn't answer is,
أما ما لا تجيب عنه فهو
how do you build an organization that harnesses this motivational power.
كيف تبنون منظمة تسخّر تلك الطاقة التحفيزية.
And this is where working swarmwise comes in,
وعند هذه النقطة يأتي العمل بذكاء السرب،
this is where swarm intelligence comes in.
حيث ذكاء السرب يتدخل.
Turns out that there are three factors that you optimize for --
اتضح أن هناك ثلاث عوامل نعمل على تحسينها من أجل --
and each of these are in complete opposite to what you learn at a business school.
وكل واحد منها في تناقض تام مع ما تعلمتموه في كلية التجارة.
But it works.
لكن الأمر ينجح.
We know it works.
نحن نعلم بأنه ينجح.
We have people in many, many parliaments to prove it.
لدينا ممثلين في العديد من البرلمانات.
Those three factors are: speed, trust and scalability.
وهذه العوامل الثلاثة هي: السرعة والثقة والتدرج.
We optimize for speed by cutting bottlenecks out of the loop,
نحسن من السرعة بإزالة العقبات من المعادلة،
cutting them out of the decision loop.
إخراجها من دائرة صنع القرار.
That means cutting yourself out of the decision loop,
هذا يعني إخراج أنفسكم من دائرة صنع القرار،
which can be hard.
وهذا أمر صعب.
But you've got to communicate your vision so passionately, so strongly,
لكنكم أوصلتم رؤيتكم بحماس وقوة
that everybody knows what the goal is
لدرجة أن كل واحد يعرف ما هو الهدف
and can find something, some step
ويمكنه تقديم شيء ما أو القيام بخطوة
that takes the movement just a little closer to that goal.
تحمل الحركة خطوة أقرب نحو الهدف.
And when tens of thousands of people do that on a weekly basis,
وعندما يفعل ذلك العشرات من الآلاف من الناس بشكل أسبوعي،
you become an unstoppable force.
تصبحون قوة لا يمكن إيقافها.
We had a three-person rule in our organization,
نعمل في منظمتنا بقاعدة الأشخاص الثلاثة،
saying that if three self-identified volunteers in the movement
بحيث إذا كان هناك ثلاث متطوعين في الحركة
were in agreement that something was good for the movement,
متفقين على أن الأمر جيد لها،
they had the green light from the highest office
يتلقون الضوء الأخضر من أعلى هيئة فيها
to go ahead and act in the name of the organization,
للمضي قدماً والتصرف باسم المنظمة،
including spending resources.
بما في ذلك استعمال الموارد.
When you talk about this kind of empowerment
عندما تتحدثون عن هذا النوع من التفويض
to traditional businesspeople,
لرجال الأعمال التقليديين،
they think you belong in a zoo.
يعتبرون أنك مجنون.
But you know what?
لكن هل تعلمون؟
I led this organization for five years,
لقد قدت هذه المنظمة لخمس سنوات،
there were 50,000 registered members
وكان هناك 50.000 عضو مسجل بها
and many, many more anonymous activists.
والكثير من النشطاء المجهولين.
It was not abused once.
لم يسأ استخدامها قط.
Everybody had the key to the treasure chest.
الجميع كانت لديه مفاتيح صندوق الكنز.
It was not abused one single time.
ولم يسأ استعمالها قط.
Turns out when you give people the keys to the castle,
لقد اتضح أنه عندما تمنحون الناس مفاتيح القصر،
and look them in the eye and say, "I trust you,"
وتنظرون في أعينهم وتقولون: "أنا أثق بك"
they step up to the plate.
فإنهم يتفانون من أجلكم.
And that's a beautiful thing to see happen.
وهذا أمر من الرائع مشاهدته يحدث.
Obviously, not everything went according to plan,
وبالطبع، فليست كل الأمور تسير وفق المخطط،
but that's a different thing.
لكن هذا أمر مختلف.
We made mistakes. We should expect mistakes.
نرتكب الأخطاء. وعلينا توقع حدوثها.
If you're pioneering something, that means you must, by definition,
إن كنتم رائدين في شيء ما، فهذا يعني أن عليكم، بالضرورة،
venture into the unknown.
خوض غمار المجهول.
When you're trying the unknown, some things won't go as planned.
وعندما تخوضون في المجهول، لابد لأمر ما ألا يسير وفق المخطط له.
That's part of the definition of venturing into the unknown.
هذا جزء من تعريف خوض غمار المجهول.
To find the great, you must allow mistakes to happen.
لبلوغ الثريا، عليكم بأن تتقبلوا حدوث الأخطاء.
So you must communicate that we expect some things to go wrong
لذا عليكم إعلام محيطكم أنكم لا تتوقعون بأن تسير كل الأمور كما يجب
to create a risk-positive environment.
لخلق مناخ إيجابي تجاه المخاطرة.
Therefore we optimize for iteration speed.
وبالتالي نحسن من سرعة التكرار.
Meaning that we try, we fail, we try again, we fail faster,
أقصد أننا نحاول ونفشل، ونحاول مجدداً ثم نفشل بشكل أسرع،
we fail better, we try again, we fail better again.
نشعر بشكل أفضل، فنحاول مجدداً، فنفشل بشكل أفضل مرة أخرى.
Maybe after we've tried 15 times, we've mastered some specific subject,
وربما بعد محاولتنا 15 مرة، نتمكن من إتقان بعض المواضيع المعينة،
so you want to minimize the time it takes to try those 15 times.
وبالتالي نبحث عن كيفية تقليص الوقت الذي تستغرقه تلك المحاولات 15.
We optimize on trust. We encourage diversity.
نحن نحسن بناء الثقة. ونشجع التنوع.
You need to communicate your vision so strongly
عليكم إيصال رؤيتكم بلغة واضحة
so that everybody can translate it into their own context
ليتمكن كل فرد بالمجموعة من ترجمتها ضمن سياقه الخاص
because language is an incredibly strong
لأن اللغة هي أداة جد قوية
inclusionary and exclusionary social marker.
للإدماج والإقصاء الاجتماعي.
This one-brand-fits-all message --
مبدأ الشعار الواحد الصالح لكافة الرسائل --
forget it!
انسوه!
That's what they teach you at business school -- it doesn't work.
هذا ما علموكم في كلية التجارة -- هذا لا ينجح.
Or at least, it doesn't give you the cost-efficiency advantage
أو على الأقل، لا يحقق لكم أفضلية الفعالية في التكلفة
of working swarmwise.
للعمل بذكاء السرب.
This leads to a lot of different approaches tried in parallel
هذا يؤدي إلى مقاربات كثيرة مختلفة مجربة بالتوازي
in different social groups
في مجموعات اجتماعية مختلفة
who try out different methods of working toward the goal.
تجرب مختلف الطرف للعمل لبلوغ الهدف.
Some of them will work
البعض منها سينجح
but in order to find the great ones, you need this diversity.
لكن من أجل العثور على أفضلها أنتم بحاجة إلى التنوع.
And you need to communicate that we need that diversity.
وعليكم أن توصلوا ذاك الشعور بأننا بحاجة إلى ذلك التنوع.
If somebody on this side does not understand
إذا لم يفهم أحدهم فيما يخص هذا الجانب
what those guys are doing,
ما تحاول فعله تلك المجموعة،
that's OK because we all trust each other to work for the better of the movement.
فلا بأس، لأننا جميعاً نثق أننا نعمل لصالح الحركة.
And it's OK that I don't understand their social context.
ولا بأس، إن لم أفهم سياقهم الاجتماعي.
I'm not expected to -- I understand my social context.
فذلك ليس ما ينتظر مني -- أنا أفهم سياقي الاجتماعي.
I contribute with something I know.
أساهم بما أعرفه.
Make people aware of this diversity.
جعل الناس تعي ذلك التنوع.
Finally, scalability. Get feet on the ground.
في النهاية، التدرج. كونوا واقعيين.
Again, in business school, they teach you to use a lean organization.
مرة أخرى، في كلية التجارة، علموكم استعمال هياكل صغيرة.
Forget that.
انسوا ذلك.
Just scale up the organization from the get-go.
يكفيكم إنشاء هيكل يتدرج صعودا منذ خطوة البداية.
Start with 10,000 empty boxes and an org chart
ابدأوا بـ 10.000 خانة فارغة وهيكل تنظيمي
covering down to every minor city.
يغطي كل مدينة صغيرة.
When you have lots and lots of small responsibilities
عندما تحصلون على الكثير والكثير من المسؤوليات الصغيرة
in such a scaffolding that supports the swarm,
في ذاك الهيكل الداعم لجسد السرب،
supports the activists,
وللنشطاء،
you'll find that these boxes in the org charts
فستلاحظون بأن تلك الخانات في الهيكل التنظيمي
are getting filled in quite rapidly,
بدأت تمتلئ بسرعة كبيرة،
and they start to get filled in beyond your horizon
وأنها بدأت تمتلئ بما يتعدى توقعاتكم
with people you've never heard of.
وبأشخاص لم تسمعوا عنهم من قبل.
And so, this swarm keeps growing to tens of thousands of people,
وبالتالي، يستمر ذاك السرب في النمو إلى العشرات من الآلاف،
each taking on something small with very, very decentralized mandate
كل واحد يتكلف بتفصيل صغير باستقلالية تامة
to act on the organization.
للتصرف ضمن التنظيم.
And this is when a swarm intelligence emerges.
وعند هذه المرحلة يظهر ذكاء السرب.
This is when you have this beehive logic where everybody knows what's to be done.
في هذه المرحلة يصبح لديكم منطق خلية النحل حيث كل فرد يعلم ما عليه فعله.
Everybody is taking their own small steps towards it.
كل فرد يخطو بخطى صغيرة نحو الهدف.
So the swarm starts to act as a coherent organism.
فيبدأ السرب بالتصرف كتنظيم متناغم.
And it's amazing to watch.
وهو أمر مدهش.
This is when you're awarded by the cost-efficiency advantage
في هذه المرحلة تجازون بأفضلية فعالية في التكلفة
over your competitors
مقارنة بمنافسيكم
by two orders of magnitude.
بمقدار أسي هو 2.
Two orders of magnitude.
نعم بمقدار أسي هو 2.
This is not just a silver bullet.
هذه ليست مجرد وصفة سحرية.
So we've been talking a lot about the big picture today.
حسناُ، لقد تحدثنا كثيراُ عن الصورة العامة اليوم.
You can use these swarm methods for a lot of stuff.
يمكنكم استعمال مقاربات السرب في أمور عدة.
Do you want to change the world?
هل ترغبون في تغيير العالم؟
Do you want to bring clean water to a billion people?
هل ترغبون في إيصال الماء الصالح للشرب إلى مليار شخص؟
Teach three billion people to read?
تعليم ثلاثة مليارات شخص القراءة؟
Maybe you're into social change;
ربما أنكم تصبون لتغيير اجتماعي؛
you want to introduce unconditional basic income.
ترغبون أن يكون الحد الأدنى للأجور مضمون قانوناً؟
Or maybe you want to take humanity to Mars.
أو ربما ترغبون في نقل البشرية إلى المريخ؟
You can do this using these methods.
يمكنكم فعل كل ذلك بواسطة تلك المقاربات.
You can do this.
يمكنكم القيام بذلك.
It's about leadership.
الأمر متعلق بالقيادة.
It's about deciding what you want to do and telling it to the world.
الأمر متعلق بتقرير ما تريدون فعله وإخبار العالم عنه.
Because no matter whether you think you can or cannot change the world,
لأنه بغض النظر عما إذا كنتم تعتقدون بأنكم قادرين على تغيير العالم أو لا،
no matter whether you think
بغض النظر عما إذا كنتم تعتقدون
you are probably right.
أنتم على الأرجح محقين.
So one question I want everybody here to ask themselves today
لذا أريد من كل واحد هنا أن يسأل نفسه اليوم
is the observation that change doesn't just happen, somebody makes it happen --
إن كان التغيير لا يقع بالصدفة، ولكن بفعل فاعل --
do you want to be that person?
هل تودون أن تكونوا ذاك الفاعل؟
And then one last thing:
والأمر الأخير:
There's one component more that's required to work swarmwise
هناك عنصر آخر يتطلبه العمل بطريقة السرب
that I haven't mentioned yet.
لم أشر إليه بعد.
And that is fun.
وهو المتعة.
This goes beyond just enjoying your job,
لأن الأمر يتخطى مجرد الاستمتاع بعملكم،
this goes beyond having a pinball machine in the office.
أو توفر مكتبكم على لعبة الـفلِبر.
Because this is actually required to succeed in a swarmwise scenario.
لأن الأمر في الواقع يتطلب النجاح في سيناريو معين لذكاء السرب.
This is required to succeed
فالأمر يتطلب النجاح
to get that cost-efficiency advantage of two orders of magnitude.
في تحقيق أفضلية فعالية في التكلفة بمقدار أسي هو 2.
For the reason that you need to attract volunteers.
لكونكم بحاجة إلى استقطاب المتطوعين.
And people, in this aspect, are rather predictable.
وفي هذا الجانب يمكن توقع ميول الناس.
People will go to other people who are having fun.
سيتجه الناس ناحية الفريق الذي يستمتع.
In contrast, they will walk an extra mile to avoid people who are not having fun.
بل سيفضلون سلوك طريق أطول لتحاشي الفريق الفاقد للمتعة.
So, having fun is more than just having a pinball machine in the office.
لذا المتعة هي أكثر من مجرد توفر المكتب على لعبة فليبر.
It's an absolute and unavoidable requirement
إنها مطلب أساسي ولا مناص منه
for organizational and operational success when you're working swarmwise.
لكل نجاح تنظيمي وعملي عندما تعملون بطريقة السرب.
So, in summary --
لذا، كخلاصة --
a recipe for a swarm organization
هذه هي الوصفة للمنظمات العاملة بنظام السرب
using these motivational methods to a huge competitive advantage.
باستعمال طرق التحفيز هذه لتحقيق أفضلية تنافسية كبيرة.
Your goal: it needs to be tangible, credible, inclusive and epic.
يجب أن يكون هدفكم: ملموساً واقعياً وشاملاً وملحمياً.
Your organization needs to be optimized for speed, trust and scalability.
منظمتكم بحاجة لأن تكون محسنة للسرعة والثقة والتدرج.
You need to enjoy yourselves.
أنتم بحاجة للاستمتاع بوقتكم.
And that will reward you
وهذا سيكافئكم
with two orders of magnitude of cost-efficiency advantage.
بأفضلية فعالية في التكلفة بمقدار أسي هو 2.
Thank you.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)